Guide to the Doris Duke American Indian oral history project audio recordings 1949-1972
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Doris Duke American Indian oral history project audio recordings
1949-1972
bulk 1960-1972
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0001
American West Center
Approximately 1,400 reel-to-reel audiotapes.
The Doris Duke American Indian oral history project audio recordings (1949-1972) consist of interviews pertaining to the lives of Native Americans and their legends, customs, social and cultural beliefs, personal life experiences, and views on the urbanization of the Native American.
Organizational History
In 1966 Doris Duke funded a program to interview Native Americans on their views of history and their place in society. The program was directed by C. Gregory Crampton of the American West Center at the University of Utah. The interviews, now housed in the J. Willard Marriot Library, represent various Native American tribes from the intermountain region and non-indians who were closely associated with these tribes.
The Doris Duke American Indian oral history project audio recordings (1949-1972) consist of interviews pertaining to the lives of Native Americans and their legends, customs, social and cultural beliefs, personal life experiences, and views on the urbanization of the Native American. This collection contains reel-to-reel audiotapes that are damaged in one or more of the following ways: shedding tape, wrinkled, warping, or brittle edges. Because of the poor condition of the audio recordings some interviews are available only in transcript form (see Ms 417).
The majority of the interviews are arranged by Native American tribe.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor. CD-R duplicate copies of each item are available for patron use.
Transcripts of the interviews are located in the Doris Duke oral history project (Ms 417) in the Manuscripts Division of Special Collections. See also the Native American oral history audio recordings (A0874).
Indians of North America--Interviews; Indians of North America--West (U.S.)--Interviews; Indians of North America--History--20th century--Interviews; Indians of North America--Social life and customs; Social Classes; Sound Recordings; Oral Histories; Sound recordings
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 July 30; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 1)
  Role of Chief, migration, dreams, tribal law, communication, territories, how to become a chief, tobacco, tribal politics, food, shelters, hunting, blankets, origin, Chief Ouray, councils, clothes, role of women, pregnancy, childbirth, parent-child relations, sexual behavior, a girls first menstural period.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 1 hour 7 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by John Boyden in Salt Lake City, Utah.
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 August 13; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 2)
  Medicine Men, tribal law, council meetings, names, ear piercing, recreation, arts and crafts.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 1 hour 11 minutes.
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 August 15; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 3)
  Dance, clothes, Bear Dance, Sun Dance.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 44 minutes.
  Also see the book by Y.T. Witherspoon (1993).
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 August 17; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 4)
  Dance, food, Sun Rising Ceremony, religion, Sun Dance, medicine, Bear Dance, profanity, Medicine Man, Ghost Dance, death, names, ghosts, burial customs, water babies, folklore, farming, coming of the White Man.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 2 hours 5 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by John Boyden in Salt Lake City, Utah. Also see the book by Y.T. Witherspoon (1993).
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 August 22; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 5)
  Language, education, Medicine Men, the Sun Dance, sacred places, religion, Doctors and Medicine Men, Native American time concept.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 55 minutes.
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 August 23; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 6)
  Religion, the creation, relationship with animals, origin of races, origin of human characteristics, origin of tribal names, the coming of the white man, the Ghost Dance, Ghosts, Ute Territories, morals and virtues, bathing custom, marriage customs, sexual behavior, polygamy, justice for the unfaithful spouses.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 43 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by John Boyden.
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 September 14; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 7)
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 43 minutes.
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 September 16; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 8)
  Sun Dance and youth, story telling, youth of today, social workers and Native American relations, Federal Policy regarding education, child-parent relations, Federal Policy, Native American-Caucasian relations, Mormon-Native America relations, Non-Mormon-Native American relations, Ute-Navajo relations, language, self concepts, childhood.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 2 hours 0minutes.
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 September 19; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 9)
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 2 hours 10 minutes.
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 September 20; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 10)
  Bureau of Native American Affairs, cattle business, farming, Colorado judgment, economics.
- Connor Chapoose (Northern Ute), 1960 September 28; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 11)
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs).
- L.B Titus (Non-Native Associated with Utes), 1967 March 24; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 12)
  Arrival of Utes at Indian Creek, Caucasian-Ute relationships, cooking techniques, ear piercing, incident with a wild jackass, hunting, livestock, shelters, renegades, clothing, children, Native American laborers, ceremonies, travel, dogs, young men and women, squaws, leather work, Native American trouble.
  Reel-to-reel audiotape, CD copy
  Interviewed and recorded by Dr. Sandra Carruthers in Moab, Utah.
  Corresponding CD: A0001-13b-01 Total running time 49 minutes.
- Helen Knight (Non-Native Associated with Utes), 1967 March 25; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 13a)
  Trade, Chipeta, McCook, shopping habits of the Native Americans.
  Reel-to-reel audiotape, CD Copy
  Corresponding CD: A0001-12-01 Total running time 56 minutes.
- Claude Taylor, Stella Taylor (Non-Native Associated with Utes), 1967 March 25; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 13b)
  Taylor's places of residence, Government Allotments, burial customs, Taylor's Children, Ute dress and hair, epidemic, accounts of individual Native Americans, Ute residential areas, language, Caucasian-Native American relations, eating habits, ceremonies, migrations, children, squaws, hunting, health, water rights, trade, shopping habits, San At-Chee, Caucasian attitudes about the Native Americans.
  Interviewed and recorded by Dr. Sandra Carruthers in Fruita, Colorado.
  Corresponding CD: A0001 -12101 Total running time 56 minutes.
- Lulu Wash Chapoose Brock (Northern Ute), 1967 February 23; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 14)
  Personal history, ancestry, children, childhood, farming, customs, alcohol, tribal affairs, education, Caucasian-Native American relations, Native American agents, food, merchants, Ouray River incidents, Lulu Brock's Grandmother, Chief Ouray, artisans, community elders.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 1 hour 3 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil in Fort Duchesne, Utah.
- Charles McGee (Hualapai), 1967 April 08; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 15)
  Medicine Men, war, divorce, story telling, legends of,,.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 1 hour 5 minutes.
  Interviewed and Recorded by C. Purcell
- Elaine Naranjo (Tewa), 1967 March 04; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 16)
  Life in Utah, joining the LDS church, move to Pueblo, education, persecution of the LDS Church, recreation, youth problems, life in Santa Clara Pueblo, Brigham Young University.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 48 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by D. C. Hammond
  Tracks 1-5 Eugene Naranjo continued from A0001-17-02.
  Tracks 6-10 Elaine Naranjo.
- Eugene Naranjo (Jemez-Santa Clara, Tewa), 1967 March 04; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 17)
  Acculturation, arts and crafts, cattle business, Catholics, Protestants, Mormons, civic organizations, education, epidemics, Native American-U.S Government relations, public health, irrigation, Jemez, San Felipe, San Ildefonso, Santo Domingo, Tesuque and Zuni Pueblos, Native American Religion, personal background, Spanish Era, tourism, welfare.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 22 minutes.
  Interview continues on A0001-6-01,02 tracks 1-5.
- Ute Rehabilitation Report (Non-Native Associated with Utes), 1956; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 18)
  Purpose of rehabilitation program, the history of the project, concept of the project, results, evaluation, progress, operational philosophy, personnel, relocation program, program direction, work plans, difficulty in evaluation, recommendations, more contact between directory and field workers, submitted reports, recommend third phase, field men should know individuals eligible for program, accomplish more, increased work load, News Letters, addition to staff, invitation of more Native American participants, work with younger people, discussion about rehabilitation program.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 33 minutes.
  Donated by Lyman Tyler
- Utes Women Conference: Gwen Mulder (Non-Native Associated with Utes), undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 19)
  Adjustment to change, human resources, settling goals, education.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 23 minutes.
- Anna Early (Apache), 1968 March 22; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 20)
  Education, wellfare, population, alcohol, Bureau of Native American Affairs, language, discrimination, story telling.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 26 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by G. Thompson
- Recording unavailable (Reel 21)
  Because of the poor condition of the audio recording this interview is available only in transcript form. Please see the Doris Duke oral history project in the Manuscripts Division of Special Collections (Ms 417).
- Lemuel Paya (Havasupai), 1967 April 05; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 22)
  Funeral Ceremony, death of children, Navajo families, the first people to live in the Tuba City Area, epidemics, trading children for food, origins of the Supai name, first people to import fruit trees, food, hunting, getting red paint, discovering salt, Supai's range limit, relations between Paiute's and Supai.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 57 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by C. G. Crampton and U. Ramsey
- Lemuel Paya (Havasupai), 1967 April 05; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 23)
  Marshall family, trade in the far past, Incident with three Spaniards, Gold mining, kidnapped woman, contact between Hopi, Navajo, Apache, Supai, and George Cochise, trade between Mojaves, Supais, Hualapais, and Hopis, basket weaving, tourism, fruit orchards, alcohol, Law.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 37 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Upton Ramsey and Dr. C. Gregory Crampton in Supai, Arizona.
- Lemuel Paya (Havasupai), 1967 April 07; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 24)
  Name of Canyons and Trails, names of Chiefs and other people, names of animals, the first pistol in the territory, Supai words for various Native American Tribes, learning to speak English, Caucasian-Native American relations.
  Reel-to-reel audiotapes, compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 28 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Upton Ramsey and Dr. C. Gregory Crampton in Supai Arizona.
- Effie Hanna, Henry Hanna (Havasupai), 1967 April 07; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 25)
  Relations with Caucasian people as a small child, trade with the Hopi, trade with the Supai.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 7 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Upton Ramsey in Supai, Arizona
- Gilbert Teton (Shoshoni), 1967 May 09; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 26)
  Education, reservation life, alcohol, economics, land, religion, youth, financial aid, Civil Rights, military service, Caucasian-Native American relations.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 44 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil and Gregory C. Thompson in Durango Colorado at the Fort Lewis College.
- Lance Eagleman (Sioux), 1967 May 08; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 27)
  Education, Reservation life, alcohol, the future for the Native American, concept of time, The Native American in society, discrimination, music. The native idealist and the white realist.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 16 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil and Gregory C. Thompson in Durango, Colorado at the Fort Lewis College.
- Kay Wallis (Athapascan), 1967 May 08; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 28)
  Education, Social problems, Reservation life, Alaska, Aleut, Gonana, migration, Caucasian and Native American relations, help for the Native American.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 30 minutes.
- Gustina Smith Wilkins (Non-Native Associated with Utes), 1968 May 05; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 29)
  Life in the early days, history of Roosevelt, Utah.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 33 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Norma Denver in Roosevelt, Utah.
- Robert Jenks (Ute), Cuch Pawwannee (Ute), Hazel Wardel (Non-Native Associated with Utes), 1969 February; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 30)
  Bear Dance, Sun Dance, legends, language, population, dance.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 7 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Norma Denver in Fort Duchesne, Utah.
  Disc only contains one track which is Hazel Wardel.
- Elaine Erickson (Thlingit), 1967 June 14; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 31)
  Education, Fort Lewis College, Native American identity, life in Alaska, Reservation observations, land, Statehood, Federal Government, Native American relations, religion, alcohol, concept of time.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 46 minutes.
- Thelma Stiffarm (Gros Ventre-Cree), 1967 June 19; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 32)
  Education, The Reservation, arts and crafts, relations between the Federal Government, Anglos, and Native Americans.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 54 min
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil in Durango Colorado at the Fort Lewis College.
- Levi Baker (Southern Ute), 1967 June 20; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 33)
  Relatives on reservation, tribal history, education, discrimination, work experiences, alcohol, reservation life, legends.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 51 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil and Gregory C. Thompson in Durango, Colorado.
- Aubry Cooper (Non-Native Associated with Southern Utes), 1967 June 16; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 34)
  Fort Lewis College, Utes on Piedra River, alcohol, Tierra Amarilla, New Mexico, Chama, allotments, gold, cattle and cattle companies, land grants, Tom Burns, Dulce agency.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 4 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil and Gregory C. Thompson in Aztec, New Mexico.
- Elmer Lincoln (Navajo), 1967 June 19; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 35)
  Elmer Lincoln:
  Education, Reservations, Navajo problems, alcohol, religion, concept of time, experience in the service, Anglo-Native American relations.
  compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 33 minutes.
- Clyde Benally (Navajo), 1967 June 13; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 36)
  Clyde Benally: (Side 1 end of track 9 is Maude Darnell)
  Shalako Club, education, humor, Reservation life, Alcohol, traditions and folklore, government relations, and The Benally family.
  Reel-to-reel audiotape (35-39), compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 15 minutes.
- Maude Darnell (Non-Native Associated with Southern Utes), 1967 June 21; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 37)
  Maude Darnell: (End of track 6 is a recording lesson/practice)
  Personal Native America acquaintances, dancing, alcohol, cattle and traders, Bayfield and the Native Americans, agents.
  Reel-to-reel audiotape (35-39), compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 26 minutes.
- Joe McKnight (Non-Native Associated with Paiute), Tony Smiraldo (Non-Native Associated with Paiute and Shoshoni), Utah and West Literature Lecture-D.D Walker, 1967 April 26; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 38)
  Joe McKnight: (track 1 is partly recorded over with practice)
  Farming, horsemen, Alcohol, intermarriage, Caucasian-Native American relations, welfare, employment, education, shelters.
  Tony Smiraldo:
  Horsemanship, Caucasian influence on Native Americans, dress, alcohol, loyalty, intermarriage, Spanish ranch, incident with a Model T Ford, allotments, Reservation and non-reservation Native Americans, Native American and Spanish Horsemen, Caucasian-Native American relations, roping, horses, cattle, shelters, names, employment, begging, Government handouts, living conditions.
  D.D Walker:
  Mormon frontier, Mark Twian and the Mormons, Artemus Ward and the Mormons, Artemus Ward in the West, Artemus Ward's travel through Utah, excerpts from Mark Twain's.
  Reel-to-reel audiotape (35-39), compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 1 hour 1 minute.
- Utah and West Literature Lecture-Neal E. Lambert (Native Americans in General), 1967 June 20; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 39)
  Neal E. Lambert:
  Mormons as literary villains.
  Reel-to-reel audiotape (35-39), compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 32 minutes.
- Utah and West Literature Lecture -Levi S. Peterson and Blanche R. Cannon (Native Americans in General), 1967 June 21; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 40)
  Fiction and history, themes in Mormon literature, Mormon plays, polygamy in literature, childhood, Mormon literature.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 31 minutes.
  Recorded by The Western History Center in Salt Lake City, Utah.
- Utah and West Literature Lecture-Levi S. Peterson (Native Americans in General), 1967 June 21; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 41)
  Wildlife, buffalo slaughter, literature about buffalo hunting, character of buffalo hunters, effect of buffalo slaughter, effect of The Great Frontier on Man.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 22minutes.
- Utah and West Literature Lecture-Robert Steensma and D.D Walker (Native Americans in General), 1967 June 22; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 42)
  Side 1) Robert Steensma:
  Homesteaders, homesteaders in fictional literature, homesteaders in autobiographical literature, homesteaders in historical literature.
  Side 2) D.D Walker:
  The Native American in early American Literature, the Native American in historical novels.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 15 minutes. Recorded by The Western History Center in Salt Lake City, Utah.
- Utah and West Literature Lecture-Delbert Wylder (Native Americans in General), 1967 June 22; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 43)
  The Native American in American literature, the NAtive American in the historical novel, the Native American in the fictional novel.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 59 minutes.
  Recorded by The Western History Center in Salt Lake City, UTah.
- Larry Tsosie (Navajo), 1967 June 13; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 44)
  Education, Financial Aid, Legends, Religion, Reservation life, concept of time, Shalako Club, family life, alcohol.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 2 minutes.
- J.M. Calvert (Non-Native associated with Northern Utes), 1967 June 13; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 45)
  Father as a Ute Trader, Colonel Randlett, schools, Episcopal Church, Duchesne Bridge Settlement, founding of Roosevelt, families of the Myton Area, road to Price and transportation, old photos of Native Americans, how Native Americans lived in the 1900's, Native American-Caucasian relations, memories of parents.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 9 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil in Salt Lake City, Utah.
- Henry Harris Jr. (Northern Ute), 1967 July 19; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 46)
  Family background, establishing Fort Duchesne, personal education, Allotments, Suckive and the flight to South Dakota, parents, Chambeau and Jim Bridger, African American troops at Fort Duchesne, Native American schools in Uintah Basin, Native American farmers, Chief Tabby, Colorow, Utes and Mormon relations, violence on the strip, problems of Native American people.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 1 hour 8 minutes.
- Dewey Arapoo (Northern Ute), 1967 July 29; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 47)
  Farmers, childhood, food and supply issue, agents, sign language, artisans.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil in Randlett, Utah.
- Oran F. Curry (Northern Ute), 1967 July 20; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 48)
  Education, cattle business dealings, farming, family life, preservation of crafts, information sources, hunting, Sawmill, religion, missionaries, reservations, court battle, Medicine Men, hair braiding, gold mine.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 49 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil in Neola, Utah.
- Robert Ouray (Northern Ute), 1967 July 18; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 49)
  Migration, farmers, Chinese merchant, Red Moon, Chiefs, agents, present condition of tribes, dances, education, sign language, allotments, Curry Brothers, travel to Pennsylvania.
  Available compact disc copy (1 CD) Total running time 52 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neli in Randlett, Utah.
- Bessie Owens Kohl (Non-Native associated with Northern Utes), 1967 July 21; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 50)
  Sources of information, politics, alcohol, shooting incident, farming decline, causes of poverty, water rights, epidemics, medical care, influentail Native Americans, duke Oral history, education, missionaries.
  Available compact disc copy (2 CDs) Total running time 1 hour 19 minutes.
  Interviewed and recorded by Floyd A. O'Neil in Heber, Utah.
- F. Vern Briscoe (Non-Native Associated with Shoshoni), 1967 July 23; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 51)
  Incidents with Navajos, panic of 1893, crossing the San Juan, confrentation with the Crow, attitude about the Navajo, trade, Caucasian-Native American relationships, Idaho Native Americans, Native American farmers, differences between the Shoshoni and Bannock people, Native American Prison sentence, Vern Briscoe's mother, Massacre, burial customs, Caucasian children looters, Squaw giving birth, Grandpa Briscoe, Caucasian attitudes, intermarriage, Native American Agents.
  Interviewed and recorded by Raymond G. Briscoe in Rigby, Idaho.
- Mr. and Mrs. Timbimboo (Shoshoni), 1967 July 25; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 52)